[Music]
the picture we have been working is if
you have a mapping a map from a manifold
itself you Tred to draw the graph of
that mapping that was the interesting
idea the diagonal and
you look at a graph like this which we
denoted by GMA and the fixed points are
exactly the intersections of that graph
with the diagonal as we saw indeed if
you are here this point does not move it
has the same value and we saw that the
left set
number Lambda of f is simply defined to
be the intersection number between the
diagonal and graph this intersection
number is counted plus or minus add them
all
together so you look at those
intersections and assign a plus or minus
and add them together and left sh fix
Point
theorem was the almost obvious statement
that if this number defet number is non
zero then there must exist F
[Applause]
points
obvious because if there are no fixed
points then let just number is zero so
that's what we had yesterday now it will
be nice in practice and bless you to be
able to calculate Le numbers of various
Maps what I mean by calculate well
usually in many
applications such a mapping is given by
formulas yeah suppose that you have a
formula we already saw one example
yesterday an important one which to a
point in the plane to the point in the
plane can you calculate is there an
algorithm for calculating leftest number
and the answer is yes so I'd like to
begin by stating that
for and proving it this use is a little
linear so please be patient with me um
suppose that the our map is given by
coordinates so locally specified
expressed by coordinates
in
coordinates as in the standard
way yeah
for the assignment of X1 through xn and
you have the first component of the map
if you like this is y equals um
something like this and then there are M
components because I'm mapping an M
dimensional manifold to an M dimensional
manifold
suppose that you have an expression of f
like this explicit expression then it
turns out that the left number can be
calculated explicitly also the left
number of
f you remember what this letter
is Cap Lambda that's right is equal to
the sum over all the fixed
points of the function so you have to
find the fix Point still unfortunately
but you will see how this simplifies in
practice and then you calculate the
determinant you have guessed because it
has to do with orientation of the
following
quantity F
Prime
minus
I and this F Prime is culated at
xus so that's the X and that's where the
X X appears what is this I well you can
guess that is the identity Matrix what's
the size of this identity Matrix you
think M by m exactly M by
m identity Matrix one along the diagonal
zero of
diagonal and this is because this
derivative is also an M bym Matrix do
you remember um we discussed this with
various people yesterday in particular
old way where where is she today she's
not sitting here um so you use the
yakobian you take the partial
derivatives of the first component
partial derives and then you arrange
them in a matrix and that's what it is
so if you calculate this sign you get
the um dous
number in order to convince you that
this does have a chance of being
correct let's draw a picture when m
equal 1 in one dimensional case the
picture is easy to draw
this is M this is M and that's diagonal
and then there is a graph which might
look like
this okay often this kind of picture
you're beginning to understand is an
abstract symbolic metaphorical picture
it's like modern art if you like it
represents a situation in a suggestive
way to us so that we understand but
usually such a picture is not a literal
picture when I for example draw a curve
like that I don't really mean that the
graph is a curve sometimes the graph
might be a surface and so but in 1D one
dimensional case this is literally true
what you're seeing is actually true so
the diagonal is a straight line at 45°
and graph is this Cur so in a situation
like this according to the standard
orientation that we took in the
convention number one yesterday well so
the diagonal is oriented like this the
curve or the graph is oriented like this
and the ambient orientation is like this
so
here the sign is Plus in that in that at
that point this corresponds in terms of
the
derivative to the statement that at this
point
x minus what is the 1 by one identity
matrix it's just one is
positive and that's true the derivatives
the slope is larger than one and
similarly you have guessed already
what's going to happen the corresponding
picture for the negative case looks like
that here if you look at the picture is
negative
because um Delta the diagonal and the
graph are like this 1 two and that's the
opposite orientation to the ambient or
orentation so this corresponds
to the derivated at this point the fixed
point being less than one that is that
and because the determinant in one by
one case is just number this illustrates
the formula that we have to
prove this formula then at least in one
dimensional case seems plausible
plausible means that we cannot yet check
it but it's believable it seems to be
true that's what closable means
okay let's now prove it as I say we need
albra bless you
again suppose that we write E1 through
em as usual the orientation basis for
M what I really means that there's a
local frame and then those
vectors Define the orientation for that
local chart but that's good enough now
in order to simplify the calculation a
little we shall introduce a new
notation each of these is is a vector
It's s a long thing like this with 1 2
three M components you can see that
right and there are M of them so we're
going to put those vectors one first
Vector two vector and so on all the way
to the m Vector put them together in a
box and regard it as a
matrix in other words in this Matrix the
First Column as we call it is E1 and
then second col and then M column is E M
I hope this notation is clear and we
shall denote this Matrix that we get by
putting together as columns all those
basis vectors orienting basis as
e yeah okay that's the Matrix e and so e
is M by m m by m
Matrix
now let's write down then what the
orientations are for Delta gamma and
ambient space ambient product
space here is what they look like in
explicit
formulas these induced orientations as
defined yesterday are as
follows this was the convention one from
yesterday for Delta M what are the basis
vectors that Define the orientation if
you calm down not panic and think about
it it's simply
this are you calm I'm not panicking the
Delta basis for Dela was the long Vector
of two M components where you copy E1
and then directly E1 second Vector is E2
directly underneath E2 and so on so this
is what the bases and for Delta M to be
precise the First Column second column
third column and so on all the way to
the m columns um the
the basis for Delta M okay and for gamma
can
anybody is anybody imaginative enough to
tell me what this is you remember for
gamma the basis was E1 and underneath we
had the derivative of f applied to E1 in
the second column E2 derivative F
applied to E2 and so on so what do you
think
the basis will look like in terms of the
Matrix e and
underneath F Prime and
derivative applied to e that's all is
and if you look at the first second
third columns and so on you see the
orienting basis I'd like to remind you
that this F Prime is a matrix M by
matrix that is called Yia okay and
finally for the excuse me for the
ambient space mty plus M it is Easy E
and underneath it's zero because the
defining basis starts with E1 and zero
underneath E2 Z underneath at some point
you get e m and zero the next Vector is
z E1 and so on so the basis looks like
this so that's an 2 m by 2 m Matrix and
this zero natur represent M by m zero
Matrix
yeah so it's a
big list of
zeros
okay
well let's suppose that X is a fixed
Point okay and I'm going to be slightly
ring my language each fixed point and
let's think of a fixed Point as a
point with coordinates x and x the same
coordinates so I'm going to write it as
um this intersect gamma GMA
F okay each fixed
point we must decide whether it has a
sign plus or minus one so contributes
let's decide which one it is depending
on those
quantities + one or - one accordingly
as the following conditions
hold the condition for plus one is that
the orientation defined by this and this
matches the orientation defined by
this okay so that means that if you
calculate a
determinant consisting of this and this
and that
is determinant of e e
and E fime * e that's an 2 m by 2 Matrix
and deterant and the determinant of that
the
ambient they have the matching or the
same orientation if those two
determinants have the same sign plus
plus or minus minus they have the
mismatched or opposite orientations if
those determinants have the opposite
signs plus minus or minus plus so all we
have to worry about is the signs of
those determinants note that the value
the magnitude of those determent is
irrelevant you see because if you have a
vector like this like this one two
that's positive if I have a vector like
this and like this the determinant will
be much larger but it's still plus it
doesn't matter the size but what matters
is a
sign sign rather than size so so
accordingly as whether those and those
two determinants have the same sign or
the opposite
sign same or the
opposite opposite
signs thus we are reduced to Computing
the determinant so please remember that
this is the orientation basis for the
diag this part is the orientation basis
for gamma and this whole thing is the
orientation basis for M
crn
okay I come over
here now how shall we decide whether
they have the same sign or not here is
how look
at the first determinant and we shall
try to manipulate this determinant
transform it so us make it look like
this
determinant so what we start with is
this deter
now you have learned I presume a long
time ago how to do things to determine
in order to calculate it how to do
things
that don't change the value deter do you
remember for example that you can take
the First Column and add it to the
second column
but that doesn't change the determinant
or take some rows and add add them or
subtract them from some rows and it
doesn't change and
So geometrically speaking by the way
you're sharing the volume but that's a
side remark so let's calculate it like
this I'm going to think of it
as those four boxes and what I shall do
is to
take these rows SW away from those
rows is that clear so I take the first
row from the M plus first row second row
from the M plus second row and so on and
M Row the bottom of the stop part from
the 2 m Row the bottom of the lower half
and the what's going to happen ah no
sorry that's not what I'm going to do in
fact I could have done it too but uh
okay let's do it like this so then eus E
I get zero and here here I get the E and
here I get fime of e minus E that's what
I get
right okay but now please remember that
this is a box M by m and this is M by m
and that's a big zero so if you
calculate the determinant of this it is
simply equal to the determinant of e
which corresponds to
that times the determinant of this
box
that doesn't it doesn't matter what this
is I can do a little better you see this
is equal to inside this second
determinant is f Prime minus the
identity time e and determinant is
multiplicative if you have the
determinant of a is the same as determin
of a * determinant of B so this is equal
to determinant of e s I can take it out
times determinant of f Prime minus the
identity Matrix on the one hand on the
other hand
determinant which defines the
orientation for the ambient space the
other determinant is e 0 0 e to begin
with so that's straightforward it is
equal to deter V
squ compare these two things deter V squ
because it's square of a scalar some
number it's always positive that's
always positive so these two things will
have the same sign or the opposite sign
depending on whether this is a plusus
one and that's exactly the sign being
contributed you see in the
formula that's the end of the proof so
the sign
of determinant
of f primeus i is the
size Plus orus one as advertised I hope
this is
clear if you like linear algebra and if
you think it's an easy and useful tool I
hope that you overo because it is useful
and easy tool then you like this proof
If you don't feel that way well I feel I
hope that you'll feel that way one day
soon but if you don't feel that way
today either because because you haven't
studied linear algebra thoroughly or
because you haven't had enough coffee
then you can just accept this just
remember how to calculate and then we'll
see a number of
examples to show the formula in
action let's begin with an old example
from yesterday example
three which we shall now
revisit example three had the case of f
which was mapping from R2 to
R2 I confess that in this situation R2
is not a closed manifold so left Chet's
ideology left's philosophy is not really
applicable here because we are talking
about the intersection number and in
know for the intersection about the
isotopy invariant in order for it to be
powerful we have to have closed this but
we'll do the calculation to see how the
calculation goes it's an interesting
example well
it Maps the point XY to the point as you
recall x^2 - y^2 / 2 and
XY those
were the real and imaginary parts of
half of z s in Disguise as you
saw this has two fixed
points and those two fixed points have
the XY coordinates as follows 0 0 can
you check that 0 0 goes to 0 0 I hope
you can another fixed Point what do you
think is the other fix point
is what XY goes to the same point in
order to see this it's nice to remember
that this map is in fact in complex
notation Z goes to half of z
s so Zer goes to zero there's another
point which goes to the same point which
one is
it
man two inde two goes to
two in fact 2 plus I Z so two z um is
another fix Point
okay and so those are those are two
fixed points and we
shall um compute
the signs at those points at this
points I'll continue over there
sorry at this fix
points what is the determinant
of this
Matrix
oh no this Matrix but that Matrix so f
primeus i so in this case f
Prime
X let's say XY - I this is a 2x2 matrix
when I say F Prime I mean again the
yoban this is equal to the following
quantity do you remember what F Prime
was we calculate this yesterday it's x -
y y X and then I have to subtract the
identity Matrix which gives you me
this and this as you can see is x - 1 2
plus interestingly y^ 2 so this is
always
positive if you want to be completely
precise at the point 0 0 what is
this 0 - 1 2 + 0 2 which is 1 that's for
at the other fixed Point 2 0 what is
this 2 - 1 2 + 0 S that's again
positive so in either case the sign is
positive so the left sh number
unfortunately this number is not isotopy
invariant because the manifold is not
closed that's okay we're just practicing
calculation this number is + one + one
that's positive that's positive so the
sign is positive and positive is equal
to+ 2 that's how you
calculate all
right you
should recall that this makes
sense because
the equation really you're solving is 1
half of Z2 = z s and it has two simple
roots
B complex the both
positive Z = 0 and 2 that's really
what's going on
[Applause]
okay that tells us how to compute the
leest number in
practice now I will probably give you
some exercises in which you can compute
refet number by this Brute Force
approach and if need P you can program a
computer to do this kind of thing given
an explicit formula representation of a
map that you want to study but from now
on in the main part of the course we'll
be using the idea and the picture of the
left number left set fix Point theorem
rather than this formula and we'll be
deducing very striking results from just
the idea and picture of left so we will
not have so many occasions to use this
formula nonetheless this is a very
useful thing to bear in
mind